<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ordinances made by Sir William Cecill Knight of the Order of the Garter, Baron of Burghley, for the order and gouernement of xiij. poore men, whereof one to be the warden of the hospitall at Stanford Baron in the countie of Northampton, to remaine in a chest in a chamber in the sayd hospitall, locked vp in a chest with two seuerall locks, the keyes whereof to be in the custodie of the Vicar of S. Martins and the bailiffe of the manour. xx. Augusti Anno xxxix. Elizabethae Reginæ, &amp; anno domini 1597.</title>
            <author>Burghley, William Cecil, Baron, 1520-1598.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18327</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4908</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116716</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851932</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851932</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17228</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18327)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17228)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 919:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ordinances made by Sir William Cecill Knight of the Order of the Garter, Baron of Burghley, for the order and gouernement of xiij. poore men, whereof one to be the warden of the hospitall at Stanford Baron in the countie of Northampton, to remaine in a chest in a chamber in the sayd hospitall, locked vp in a chest with two seuerall locks, the keyes whereof to be in the custodie of the Vicar of S. Martins and the bailiffe of the manour. xx. Augusti Anno xxxix. Elizabethae Reginæ, &amp; anno domini 1597.</title>
                  <author>Burghley, William Cecil, Baron, 1520-1598.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Deputies of C. Barker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Almshouses --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>[Stamford Baron (England)] --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:17228:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Ordinances made by Sir William Cecill, Knight of the Order of the Garter, Baron of Burghley, for the order and gouernement of xiij. poore men, whereof one to be the Warden of the Hoſpitall at Stanford Baron in the Countie of Northampton, to remaine in a Cheſt in a Chamber in the ſayd Hoſpitall, locked vp in a Cheſt with two ſeuerall locks, the keyes whereof to be in the cuſtodie of the Vicar of S. Martins and the Bailiffe of the Manour.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>xx. Auguſti Anno xxxix. ELIZABETHAE Reginae, &amp; Anno Domini 1597.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt fiue ſhall be named, choſen and admitted alwayes by me <hi>William</hi> Lord Burghley, during my life, and after, by mine heire male that ſhalbe owner of mine houſe and Lord of Burghley, whereof the formoſt ſhalbe called the Warden of the Almeſhouſe of the Lord Burghley.</p>
            <p>The next foure, which is the vi. vii. viii. and ix. ſhall be named and admitted by the Vicar of S. Martins for the time being, and the Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffe of the Manour of Stanford Baron, in the County of Northampton, and the eldeſt Churchwarden of S. Martins, and by them that ſhall be dwellers in the Nunry, otherwiſe called S. Michaels, and in the Inne called the George of Stanford Baron, or by the greater number of them.</p>
            <p>The laſt foure, <hi>viz.</hi> the x. xi. xii. and xiii. ſhal be named and admitted by him that ſhalbe for the time Alderman of the Borough of Stanford, in the County of Lincolne, and by the Recorder of that Towne, the Steward and Bailife of the ſayd Manour of Stanford, or the more part of them, whereof the Alderman to be one.</p>
            <p>Item, the Vicar of S. Martins, or the Curate of the Church for the time being, ſhall keepe a Regiſter in writing of the names and ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names of all the ſayd poore men, which booke ſhall be kept in the Veſtry within the Chancell of S. Martins Church, and ſhall be written in order, beginning with the name of the Warden, and then of the firſt foure, and ſo following the ſecond foure, and laſtly the laſt foure, and ſhall be ſigned with the hands of the Bailife of the Manour of Stanford Baron, and of the Steward of that Manour, and ſo yerely renued as cauſe ſhall require, vpon the deceaſe or change of any of the ſayd poore men, and a double of this booke ſhall be deliuered to the Alderman of Stanford, to be kept with the Records of the Towne, thereby to know how the number ſhall continue.</p>
            <p>Item, when the warden and any other of the xii. ſhall die, or any of their places become voide, the place of ſuch as ſhall die, or become void, being either the Warden or of the number of the firſt foure, ſhall be ſupplied by the Lord of Burghley for the time being, and ſo the place of any of the ſecond foure, dying or becomming void, ſhall be ſupplied by the foreſayd Vicar, and the perſons that are authoriſed to name the ſecond company of foure: and the like ſhalbe obſerued by the Alderman of Stanford, and the others ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with him for the ſupplying of ſuch places of the laſt foure, as ſhall from time to time become void.</p>
            <p>Item, if the parties aforenamed, or the more part of them, ſhall not ſupply the void places of ſuch as haue bene firſt choſen by them within xxviii. dayes after the ſame ſhal be voide, the ſame ſhall be ſupplied by any two others of them that are authoriſed to nominate any of the ſayd xii. and in default of ſuch nomination, the Lord of the houſe of Burghley and his heires male ſhall ſupply the ſame within two moneths, and in default thereof, ſome one or two of the Feoffees or their heires (to whom the annuitie of one hundreth pounds is granted, that ſhall dwell nere to Burghley) ſhall ſupply the ſame.</p>
            <p>Item, the Warden of the houſe ſhall haue yeerely a gowncloth of three yards and of viii. s. the yard, and euery of the other ſhall haue euery yere a gownecloth of three yards at vi. s. viii. d. the yard, of ſuch colour as the Liuerie coats of the Lord Burghley or his heires ſhall be for the time, which ſhalbe prouided and bought by the Balife of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Stanford Baron, and by the ouerſight of the Vicar of S. Martins and the Alderman of Stanford.</p>
            <p>Item, in the nomination of the ſayd Warden and xii. poore men, theſe circumſtances following ſhall be obſerued, or els none otherwiſe named ſhall be allowed.</p>
            <p>FIrſt, euery one ſo to be named, ſhall be preſented in the Church of S. Martins, vpon a Sunday in the forenoone to the Vicar of the ſayd Church, and by him allowed to be of honeſt Chriſtian profeſſion, and able and well diſpoſed to ſay the Lords prayer, the Creede, and to learne to anſwere to the Ten commandements, as are preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to ſuch as are Catechiſed.</p>
            <p>Item, none ſhalbe thereto admitted, but ſuch as haue bene borne in the Counties of Northampton, Lincolne, or Rutland, or that haue dwelt for the ſpace of vii. yeeres within the ſpace of vii. miles of the Borough of Stanford, except the Lord of Burghley houſe ſhall for ſome reaſonable cauſe diſpenſe therewith, neither ſhall any be thereto allowed that is vnder xxx. yeres of age, or that hath any certeinty of liuing aboue the value of liii. s. iiii. d. by the yeere, nor any that is knowen to be diſeaſed of any Leproſie or of the Pocks called the French pocks, or of any Lunacy, or to be a common Drunkard, Barretor, or infamous for adulterie, theft, or ſuch like fault.</p>
            <p>Item, the ſayd poore men ſhall be (as nere as may be) choſen out of ſuch as haue bene either honeſt ſouldiers or workemen, as Maſons, Carpenters, or other Artizans of handy crafts, or Labourers in any works or in Huſbandry, or ſeruants that are by ſickneſſe, age, or other impediment, vnable to get their liuing by their handy worke or by dayly ſeruice, as beforetime they haue done: And if after that they ſhalbe choſen to the places, any of them ſhall fall into ſuch infirmities of infectious diſeaſes, or to be iuſtly infamed and conuinced of ſuch notable vices as aboue is in the next former Article mentioned, they ſhalbe diſplaced by them by whoſe authority they were placed, and their allowance to ceaſe within xiiii. dayes after their diſplacing, againſt which time their places ſhalbe ſupplied by ſuch as haue diſplaced them.</p>
            <p>Item, none of the ſayd xiii. poore men ſhall in Alehouſes or other places play at Cards, Dice, or any vnlawful game, but if after once warning giuen to them by the Vicar of S. Martins, or the Bailife of Stanford Baron or of the Manour of the Borough of Stanford, to forbeare from ſuch vnlawfull play, ſhall a ſecond time commit any ſuch offence prohibited, he ſhalbe remoued from his place, and ſhall receiue no more weekly reliefe, except vpon knowledge of his fault, and promiſe of amendment, he ſhalbe reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the ſayd Vicar and Bailife, and two others of the number that did firſt place him.</p>
            <p>Item, euery of theſe poore men ſhall reſort in their Liuery gownes to Common prayer euery Sunday, Wedneſday, Friday, and Holyday to S. Martins Church at Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Euening prayer, and ſhall ſit or kneele in ſome place appointed by the Churchwardens. Neither ſhall any of them be abſent from the Church at ſuch times, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iuſt cauſe by ſickneſſe, to be notified to the Vicar, and to be allowed by him. And for euery ſuch default not excuſable, the Pariſh Clerke ſhall haue vi. d. out of the weekes wages allowed to the poore man that ſhall make ſuch default.</p>
            <p>Item, there ſhalbe paid to the ſaid Warden, and to the other xii. by the Vicar of S. Martins, and the Bailife of the Manour in S. Martins Church, or by one of them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Sunday after Euening praier, theſe ſummes following, <hi>viz.</hi> To the Warden of the Hoſpitall the ſumme of iii. s. for the weeke folowing, and to euery of the other twelue the ſumme of ii. s. iiii. d. for the weeke following, ſauing to the pariſh Clerke his due for the default afore committed, (if any ſhalbe) as aboue is expreſſed, which he ſhall alſo receiue at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>Item, all theſe poore men, that ſhall bee vnmaried, and not notoriouſly ſicke, ſhall lodge euery night in the common houſe, without ſome ſpecial impediment, to be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Vicar or by the Bailiffe of the Manour of Stanford Baron, and ſuch as ſhalbe maried, may liue with their wiues out of the common houſe, ſo the ſame bee within S. Martins Pariſh, or within the Borough of Stanford, but yet they ſhall be bound one night in a moneth, to lodge with their fellowes in the common houſe, vpon paine of loſſe of one weekes wages, which ſhalbe paide to the poore mens boxe in S. Martins Church.</p>
            <p>Item, none of them ſhall goe abroade in their gownes out of the bounds of S. Martins Pariſh, or out of the Borough of Stanford, and the liberties thereof.</p>
            <p>Item, the Vicar of S. Martins, or Miniſter ſhall vpon the firſt Sunday of euery quarter of the yeere, aſſemble them together in the Church before Euening praier, and ſeuering them aſunder, ſhall heare them ſay the Lords praier, and the Creede, and to anſwere to the Commandements: and ſuch as will not in conuenient time learne, and be able to ſay the ſame, ſhalbe auoided from his roome after fourteene dayes ſpace giuen him to learne the ſame, and the Vicar or Miniſter ſhall haue for his labour v. s. eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſuch Sunday, and the Pariſh Clearke twelue pence for attending on the Vicar.</p>
            <p>Item, they ſhall euery firſt Sunday of euery quarter goe to Burghley houſe, (if the Lord of Burghley, or the Ladie his wife ſhall there keepe houſhold) and there ſhall dine at one table together in the hall, where they ſhall haue two meaſe of meate, euery meaſe of two diſhes, one with pottage and boiled meate, the other roſte, (if it bee no faſting d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y) and if it be a fiſh day, then they ſhall haue two like meaſes of white meate and fiſh. For the charges whereof, he that ſhall dwell at Burghley as the heire of the houſe, ſhall defray the ſame, or els in caſe of the abſence of the ſaid Lord Burghley, or the Ladie his wife from the houſe, paiment ſhalbe made out of the yeerely ſumme of the annuitie to the ſaid thirteene poore men after the rate of iiii. d. a peece, to be paide by the Bailiffe of the Manour, or by ſuch as ſhalbe authoriſed to receiue the annuitie, and to diſtribute it according to theſe orders, and the ſame to be allowed vpon the account.</p>
            <p>Item, if at any time he that ſhalbe mine heire of my houſe at Theobalds in Hartfordſhire, ſhal come to Burghley, or Stanford, the ſaid poore men ſhall preſent themſelues duetifully vnto him, and ſhall offer any ſeruice they can doe to him, in memorie of the Founder <hi>William</hi> Lord Burghley, Aunceſtor of the ſaid Owner of Theobalds.</p>
            <p>Item, if any doubt or queſtion ſhall hereafter ariſe vpon the wordes or meaning of theſe former Articles or Ordinances, the reſolution or determination thereof ſhall bee made, and in writing deliuered to the Vicar of S. Martins, by the Biſhop of Peterborough, or by the Deane and any one Prebendarie of the Church of Peterborough, whereunto all parties ſhall yeeld and obey.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:17228:2"/>
Item, as theſe poore men ſhall at the firſt haue their ſeuerall roomes allowed vnto them in the Almes houſe, ſo ſhall they during their liues, or their continuance in their places, continue their lodgings, and euery one as he ſhall ſucceede to the voyde place, ſo ſhall he ſucceed in the lodging without any change.</p>
            <p>Item, all the twelue ſhall at their entries openly in S. Martins Church, promiſe to be obedient to the Warden of the houſe, in all things that he ſhall aduiſe them for the obſeruation of the orders by theſe Articles preſcribed. And if any of them ſhall wilfully refuſe to obſerue the ſame, he ſhal complaine therof to the Lord Burghley for the time being, or in his abſence to the Vicar, and Bailiffe of the Manour, who ſhall remoue ſuch a wilfull perſon from the place, whereunto they that did firſt name him, ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point another.</p>
            <p>Item, during the life of me the Lord Burghley, he that is, &amp; ſhalbe my Bailiffe of my Manour of Stanford Baron, ſhal receiue the ſaid annuitie of one hundreth pounds, out of my lands heretofore called Cliffe Parke, in the Countie of Northampton, and ſhall with the priuitie of the Alderman of Stanford, or the Vicar of S. Martins, make payment thereof according to theſe orders, and the reſt that ſhal remaine vpon his yeerely accompt, to be employed on the repayre of the houſe, or vpon the poore priſoners in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Gaole in the Borough of Stanford, by the appointment of the Alderman, and the ſaid Vicar for the time being, before whom the ſaide Bailiffe ſhall make yeerely his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the ſecond day of Nouember. And after my deceaſe, if the ſaid Alderman, Vicar, and Recorder of Stanford for the time being, ſhal not like to continue the ſaide Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffe for the ſaide ſeruice, they ſhall name and appoint either ſuch as ſhall bee Bailiffe of the Borough of Stanford, or ſuch as ſhalbe Inhabitants in the Inne or houſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the George of Stanford Baron, or in the ſcite of S. Michaels Nunrie, or in default of them, ſuch other as ſhalbe meete for that ſeruice, with the conſent of the L. Burgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley for the time being, or any of two the Feoffees, which account ſhalbe alſo yeerely afore the laſt of Nouember preſented to the Lorde Burghley, if he ſhall then be reſiding at Burghley, or in his abſence from thence to ſome one of the Feoffees.</p>
            <p>Item, the ſaid annuitie ſhalbe paid by the Bailiffe or Farmors of Cliffe euery quarter of the yeere to the Bailiffe of the Manour of Stanford Baron, that is to ſay, xxv. pounds at or before the feaſt of S. Michael the Archangel, and ſo quarterly by equall portions, with which money the Bailiffe ſhall weekely make paiment of the foreſayde ſummes as afore is expreſſed. And now for the firſt paiment, he ſhall begin the firſt Sunday after the feaſt of S. Michael, and ſo continue weekely.</p>
            <p>There ſhalbe alſo prouided by the ſaid Bailiffe with the priuitie and allowance of the Alderman of Stanford, and the Vicar of S. Martins, gownes for euery of them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the value aboue mentioned, which ſhalbe deliuered to them yeerely the Saterday afore the firſt Sunday after Michaelmas.</p>
            <p>There ſhalbe alſo during the terme of twenty and one yeeres from the feaſt of S. Michael the Archangel laſt paſt, yeerely deliuered out of the woods of Cliffe Parke, thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene loades of fire wood for the ſaid thirteene poore people abiding in the ſaid Hoſpital by <hi>Roger Dale</hi> gent. the Farmer or Tenant at Cliffe Parke, his executors or aſſignes, which thirteene loades, the ſaid <hi>Roger Dale</hi> his Executors or Aſſignes are bound by couenant to cauſe yeerely to be caried to the ſaid Hoſpitall at ſome conuentient time before the feaſt of all Saints, and after the end of the ſaid xxi. yeeres, the ſaid quantity of wood ſhalbe prouided by the Bailiffe of the ſaid Mannor of Stanford Baron for the time being.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Burghley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
